BETH: The purpose of a risk assessment
is to evaluate risks or hazards, then to
remove that hazard or minimise the level
of risk by adding measures to control it.
JOE: Any event or activity can have an
element of risk to it, so it’s important
to assess any risks ahead of time and be
prepared for those risks to happen whilst
minimising the chance of them happening.
Establishing what actions can
be taken can help to minimise
the impact if it does happen.
Planning should help to prioritise
risks that are more likely
happen and cause greater impact.
BETH: When looking at risk assessment
that involves an individual with autism,
this can involve specific new activities,
or more routine everyday things.
It may be needed for a day out or
a school trip, an event, activity
or a holiday, or something really
simple like preparing a meal.
JOE: Usual methods of risk assessment
are made up of structured forms and
charts documenting any prospective
activity and the problems associated
with it such as health and safety issues.
However, this doesn’t always take
into consideration the person,
their needs, objectives and dreams.
BETH: When it comes to looking
specifically at-risk assessment
focused on activities individuals
with autism might do daily, then more
consideration needs to be given to
how the ‘risks’ can be outweighed by
the benefits of taking those risks.
JOE: A risk assessment can be completed
as part of other assessments to assess
the environment both physical and social
for any risks to an individual with
autism, taking a holistic approach.
BETH: Risk assessment can give an insight
into the level of risk an individual will
face during any activity within a home,
educational or work environment, but
can be more specifically focused on new
risks or new challenges going forward.
It can also consider how an individual’s
behaviour within the situation or
activity may affect the outcome.
JOE: Individuals with autism are often
so single-minded about their interests
that they are unaware of the effect
that their actions may have on others,
or any consequences to themselves.
Therefore, risk assessments need to
not just focus on the immediate health
and safety risks, but the overall
well-being of an individual going
forward long-term, and the benefits that
can be gained by positive risk taking.